Guide to the Bernhard Knollenberg Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence (Chronological), 1560-1943; Series I; 5.5 linear feet (13 Boxes)
  - Order from Walter Spooner to Col. Benedict Arnold for him to deliver the livestock in his possession to Col. James Easton. Photostat copy of the original, 1775 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Bostwick, Elisha, 1748-1834, photostat copy of his service with the Connecticut infantry, 1775 July 12 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - ALS, Col. B. Harrison to Gen. George Washington; tells Washington what is happening in Philadelphia, recommends certain people to the General, indicates that now colonial currency will be printed soon. Copy of original, 1775 July 21 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to printer. Copy, 1775 July 27 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - AL, Horatio Gates to Col. Baldwin; concerning the care of the poor sent from Boston to Chelsea, 1775 August 1 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - ALS, Richard Peters to George Panton; urging Panton to attend the annual convention despite the unrest in the nation. With Photostat, 1775 August 30, 31 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - ALS, Col. James Warren, 1726-1808, to [?]; on arriving safely at Philadelphia. Mentions Adams, Cabot, Cushing and Hancock. Photostat of Original, 1775 September 28 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - ALS, Thomas Lynch, 1794-1779 to [?]; discussion of the affairs in the Carolinas, lack of supplies, and the impending journey of a convention delegate to New England. Photostat of Original, 1775 December 8 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Governor Ward; seeks to correct a misunderstanding that the poor were not those who were making money on the war, but rather the merchants and wealthy planters. The colonies must work together in harmony. The need to retain the arms of those whose enlistment is up, but despite all colonial troops are not well armed. Photostat of Original, 1775 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - ALS, Philip Schuyler to George Washington; telling of the death of Montgomery, the wounds of Arnold, and the dangerous situation of the troops and pro-Colonial Cause Canadians. He pleads for reinforcements, 1776 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to [?]; George Washington tells of the capture and fortification of Dorchester Heights and American cannon fire into Boston and the lack of return fire from the British. Photostatic Copy, 1776 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - TLS, John Adams to Gen. Horatio Gates; Adams urges the driving of the British from Boston and when that is done, for Gates to block the harbor. Adams feels that we have waged only half a war. Speaks of the Parliament's Act of Independency that sunders America from the Empire, 1776 March 23 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - ALS, Nathaniel Shaw to Christopher Leffingwell urging the forwarding of cannon as soon as possible. Washington's letter of same date included. Photostat of Original, 1776 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - ALS, George Washington to Esek Hopkins; warning him of an impending British blockade of New London and asking that cannon and stores be sent to George Washington. Photostat of original, 1776 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to John Adams; liberty and safety can only be secured with independence; a generally harsh letter to Adams in reply to his letter of 23 Mar 1776, 1776 April 23 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - ALS, John Adams to Horatio Gates; a reply to Gates letter of 23 April in attempt to soothe the General and enable the General to understand the politician's position. Photostat of Original, 1776 April 27 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to John Adams; met Col. Clinton, speaks of Sullivan's move to Albany and from there with 10,000 men to Quebec; praise of Arnold, wants to stay in command in Boston, but will go where the Congress wants him to. Photostat of Original, 1776 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - AL, H.K. to John Adams; discussing the most valuable texts on the art of warfare that should be made available and read by American officers. Photostat, 1776 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - TLS, Nathanael Greene to [?]; urges recruitment of new troops before the British increase their forces, 1776 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - ALS, Dr. T.B. Chandler to George Panton; tells Panton that 40 pounds in relief funds for loyal American clergy is on its way to him, but more funds are difficult to come by. With Photostat of Original, 1776 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - ALS, John Adams to Horatio Gates notifying Gates that he has been placed in command of Canadian forces and calling to his attention and favor an Adjutant named Rice already in Canada. Photostat copy of original, 1776 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Typed copy of a letter from Horatio Gates to John Adams, stating that the army in Canada is in peril and that the army is split into many segments, 1776 June 24 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Memorial of the judge advocates concerning rules and articles for the government on the subject of court martials in the service, 1776 June (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Estate left by A. Hummell to Benedict Arnold; Value 112 pounds, 1776 June (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Typed copy of a letter John Adams to Mr. Chase, speaks of the Declaration of Independence, defense measures for New York, 1776 July 9 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to John Hancock) writes of the retreat to Ticonderoga; the epidemic of smallpox; the attempt to check the British advance with a hastily prepared naval force. Photostat copy of the original, 1776 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Typed copy of a letter from Horatio Gates to John Adams, complains of lack of power; the poor state of the army; the unfair report of Samuel Chase to congress; joy over Independence Declaration; need for instructions to the paymaster, 1776 July 17 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Typed copy of a letter from John Adams to Horatio Gates, excuse for Samuel Chasers report; need to stamp out smallpox; need for regular returns and accounts every month, 1776 August 13 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - TL by Horatio Gates to John Adams; the appointment of Mr. Rice as major; asks favor for Lieut. Col. Baldwin, an engineer; expresses hope to hold enemy if the British can be kept from Staten Island, 1776 August 23 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - ALS Jonathan Trumbull, governor of Connecticut, to Governor Cooke of New York, discussing plans for the defense of New York City and eastern Long Island, 1776 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - ALS, Jonathan Trumbull to William Williams; discusses the condition of the American army and the fleet and the controversy about Gen. Schuyler, whose character he warmly defends, 1776 September 22 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - ALS, Elisha Buss to John Buss; family letter from a brother at home to one in the army, 1776 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to [?]; relates the preparation for going into winter quarters and the expiration date of some of the state militia; asks for replacements. Photostat of Original, 1776 November 27 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - ALS, Gen. (Mad) Anthony Wayne to Horatio Gates; tells the conditions of Fort Ticonderoga-many sick, enlistments up, poor food, hands tied by headquarters. Photostat of Original, 1776 December 1 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - LS, George Washington to [?]; giving permission to go to Philadelphia, but wishing the addressee would go to Bristol instead. Photostat of original, 1776 December 23 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Virginia Declaration of Rights. Photostatic copy, 1776 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - ALS, Governor Schuyler (New York) to Gen. Washington; success in New Jersey campaign; Albany. Photostat, 1777 January 30 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - LS, Jonathan Trumbull to Jabor Huntington (written in hand of William Williams), Sheriff, signer of Declaration of Independence. London, 1777 February 11 (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - ALS, William Duer and Jonathan Tompkins to Major General Wooster; disposition of troops. Photostat, 1777 February 13 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - ALS, Castriss, Marshall of France, to M. DeCerdaine (French); regarding property and demands concerning it. Paris, 1777 February 28 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - ALS, Roger Sherman to William March; regarding various requisitions for men and supplies for the army. Photostatic copy, 1777 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - ALS, John Adams to Nathanael Greene; stating that we should match our men, man-for-man, with the British; officers are not leading the men correctly, abandon the defensive plan - letter never sent - too impolite, 1777 April 13 (?) (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - ALS, Richard Peters (War Office) to (?) urging the removal of stores and arms to a safe place, perhaps near Baltimore, stating the War Office. would pay freight, 1777 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates of John Hancock, need for troops and supplies to hold Ticonderoga, newly recruited regiments are understrength; conference with Governor Trumbull to obtain more troops and supplies; apathy seems to reign, 1777 April 22 (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - ALS, General William Heath to General George Washington, introduction of General Conway from France; information on the state of France in records the American cause; indicates that some gunsmiths might be persuaded to come to America. Photostat copy of original, 1777 April 26 (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - AL, John Adams to Nathaniel Greene, pages 3, 4, 5 only; describes, by analogy, the art of intrigue and its use in the art of war. Photostat copy of the original, 1777 May 24 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - ALS, Philip Schuyler to Philip Livingston, James Duane and William Duer, army has run down during his absence; provisions are wanting; inadvisable to maintain long lines at Ticonderoga. Photostat copy of original, 1777 June 14 (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - ALS, General Arthur St. Clair to John Hancock, explains dire straits at Ticonderoga; fear of British attack. Photostat copy of original, 1777 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 143)
  - ALS, Israel Putnam to (2), explains all is in readiness to leave via ship from Peekskill as soon as sufficient vessels arrive. Photostat copy of original, 1777 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - ALS, Joseph York (Lord Dover) to Sir William Hamilton a letter of introduction of one Mr. Tenhove, the nephew of Grostier Tagel, a friend of Yorks's, 1777 July 2 (Box 3, Folder 145)
  - Extract of a letter, George Washington to the Council of Safety, Washington fails to understand why General St. Clair evacuated Fort Ticonderoga; hopes to protect Albany; complains militia disappear as quickly as they come. Photostat copy of original, 1777 July 9 (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - Petition to Brigadier General Conway from the Field Officer of his Brigade concerning the appointment of Rev. Dr. William Rogers as chaplain. Photostat copy of original, 1777 July 19 (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - ALS, General Philip Schuyler to George Washington, militia enlistments up; explanation why Ticonderoga evacuated; only a few continental troops; fear of enemy attack; need for reenforcements or that section of the country will be lost, 1777 July 22 (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - ALS, Joseph Wright to Governor Thomas Johnson of Maryland, contains the statement of a case of an American, captured by the British, let go on parole being re-enlisted and going to fight again without having been exchanged, 1777 July 27 (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - ALS, General Arthur St.Clair to Horatio Gates, states that he couldn't hold Ticonderoga with 2,000 men, especially since 1/4 of them would be up in enlistment soon. Photostat copy of the original, 1777 August 1 (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - Role of Captain John Bayley's Company, Joseph Marshe's Regiment. 36 men listed, 1777 August 18 (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - Photostat of the Connecticut Courant for the week of Sept. 1, 1777, 1777 September 1
  - ALS, General J. Conway to (?), requests command of a bridgade of light infantry, citing his experience in command under fire as credentials of his bravery. Photostat copy of original, 1777 September 1 (Box 3, Folder 153)
  - ALS, General Conway to (?.), the use of engineers to lay out campsites and fortification before the troops arrive so they can begin; at once is very successful. Photostat copy of original, 1777 September 2 (Box 3, Folder 154)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to John Hancock, the victory at Bennington has helped build militia strength, need of money by the commissary; need for blank commission papers to commission officers. Photostat copy of original, 1777 September 13 (Box 3, Folder 155)
  - ALS, General Philip Schuyler to Colonel Parrick, expressing hope that the arrival of Gates will compel General Burgoyne, to leave Saratoga. Photostat copy of the original, 1777 September 13 (Box 3, Folder 156)
  - ALS, General Philip Schuyler to (?), the British have withdrawn, none of the buildings at Saratoga were burned. Photostat copy of the original, 1777 September 14 (Box 3, Folder 157)
  - ALS, Israel Putnam to John Hancock, problems of delaying the British if they land on Long Island or New Jersey. Photostat copy, 1777 September 16 (Box 3, Folder 158)
  - ALS, by General Conway to (?), complains of being overlooked, pushes his own ability and demands the rank of major general. Photostat copy, 1777 sep 25 (Box 3, Folder 159)
  - ALS, Benedict Arnold to Horatio Gates, complains of mistreatment, of only being a cypher in the army, will stay despite Gate's jealousy, urges the general to action. Photostat copy, 1777 October 1 (Box 3, Folder 160)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to John Hancock, information that Burgoyne has only 15 days' provisions, Gates will hold off enemy's assault and cut off retreat. Photostat copy, 1777 October 4 (Box 3, Folder 161)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to George Washington, enemy still holding same camp and have fortified it, the British have to make a move within two weeks; need for munition supply. Photostat copy, 1777 October 5 (Box 3, Folder 162)
  - ALS, Richard Peters to General Anthony Wayne, the avarice of the people hurts the revolution, we should pursue an offensive conduct of the war. Photostat copy, 1777 October 11 (Box 3, Folder 163)
  - ALS, Israel Putnam to Horatio Gates, situation unchanged along the North River. Putnam has about 2,500 continental and militial troops but mostly militia. Photostat of original, 1777 October 13 (Box 3, Folder 164)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to John Hancock, letter with the convention of Saratoga and the surrender of Burgoyne. Photostat copy, 1777 October 18 (Box 3, Folder 165)
  - ALS, General Conway to John Hancock, tells that he sent an honest report and just criticism of the army; that he still deserves a higher rank. Photostat copy, 1777 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 166)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to (General Burgoyne) relates the treatment of wounded British Officers; asks for an exchange of Col. Ethan Allen, tells Burgoyne to stop burning houses as he leaves toward Canada. Photograph of original, 1777 October 21 (Box 3, Folder 167)
  - ALS, Benjamin Austin to Benjamin Franklin, serving as a letter of introduction of his son and asking Franklin to look out for the boy in Paris. Photograph of Original, 1777 October 25 (Box 3, Folder 168)
  - ALS, John Langdon to Benjamin Franklin, copy of articles of capitulation of Burgoyne, describes the battle of Saratoga. Photograph of Original, 1777 October 29 (Box 3, Folder 169)
  - AL, Colonel Hamilton and moves on the east side of the Hudson River mentioned in this letter segment. Photostatic Copy, 1777 November 7 (Box 3, Folder 170)
  - ALS, General Conway to (George Washington), explains that he did not wrongly criticize the army or Gates, that opinion should be exchanged between general officers, that he intends to write an account of his experiences in America, but will tell only the truth. Photostat of Original, 1777 November 9 (Box 3, Folder 171)
  - ALS, General Conway to Horatio Gates, telling Gates that he has resigned because of treatment by Congress. Photostat of Original, 1777 November 9 (Box 3, Folder 172)
  - ALS, General Conway to Horatio Gates, congratulates Gates on his new appointment, promises to send his observations on how the Army could be improved, and a plan for the Army. Photstat of Original, 1777 November 11 (Box 3, Folder 173)
  - ALS, General Burgoyne to Horatio Gates, complains of the quartering of officers, particularly Generals, thanks Gates for the good he has done. Photograph of Original, 1777 November 14 (Box 3, Folder 174)
  - ALS, General Conway to Charles Carroll (delegate to Congress from Maryland, signer of Declaration of Independence). Reasons why he resigned. Photostat of Original, 1777 November 14 (Box 3, Folder 175)
  - ALS, James Lovell to [General Gage]; tells of the poor state of the armed services, the need for men, the defeat of Burgoyne and the appearance of a European war keeps the American cause looking respectable. Photostat of original, 1777 November 27 (Box 3, Folder 176)
  - TLS, Lafayette to Major Bouchet telling Bouchet not to promise for France things that France cannot fulfill; also to take care on his journey back to France; expresses concern for the plight of Gen. Conway, 1777 December 1 (Box 3, Folder 177)
  - ALS, Rev. T.B. Chandler to Rev. George Panton; speaks of how things are in London, indicates that the Missionary Society will continue to support Panton, even though he was driven out of his mission. With Photostatic Copy, 1777 December 3 (Box 3, Folder 178)
  - TL, [?] to Lafayette; urges the retaining of Gen. Conway and Lafayette's help in the matter, 1777 December 6 (Box 3, Folder 179)
  - Extract from the minutes of the Board of War, acting on Gen. Conway's resignation, creating the post of Inspector General to be filled, as defined by Conway. Photostat of Original, 1777 December 12 (Box 3, Folder 180)
  - ALS, John Buss to Stephen Buss; describes the conditions at Valley Forge, the erection of wooden huts and the scarcity of food, 1778 January 2 (Box 3, Folder 181)
  - ALS, General Thomas Conway to [Horatio Gates]; Conway feels discriminated against, unjustly accused of conspiring against Washington. Wishes he did not have the post of Inspector General, but rather ambassador or envoy to France. Photograph of Orig, 1778 January 4 (Box 3, Folder 182)
  - ALS, General Lafayette to George Washington; urges the creation of a company manned by Frenchmen, under French Officers in Morgan's corp. Speaks of the Conway business. Urges that the office of quarter master general be established. Photostat, 1778 January 5 (Box 3, Folder 183)
  - Petition sent to John Hancock from the Brigadier General at Valley Forge, denouncing the undue promotion of General Conway. Photostatic Copy, 1778 January 6 (Box 3, Folder 184)
  - ALS, Tench Tilghman to [General Washington]; conditions at Valley Forge are good; one British raid; fear of a Junto involving Gage and Conway and others; the real reason of Bourgoyne's surrender. Photostat of original, 1778 January 18 (Box 3, Folder 185)
  - ALS, Eph. Blayne to Col. Harrison; report of an overheard conversation indicating that Conway had made a fool of the Americans. Photostatic Copy, 1778 January 18 (Box 3, Folder 186)
  - ALS, Gen. Lafayette to [George Washington]; speaks of Gen. Conway and how he has made the American Congress look foolish. Photostat of Original, 1778 January 20 (Box 3, Folder 187)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to Marquis de Lafayette; the appointment of Lafayette to command an expedition against Montreal. Photostat of original, 1778 January 24 (Box 3, Folder 188)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to Brigadier General Stark; Lafayette first in command, Conway second in command; Stark to cooperate with them. Photostat, 1778 January 24 (Box 3, Folder 189)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to Colonel John Gruton; the C.O. at Albany tells in detail the proposed plan for invading Canada and directing his cooperation. Photostat of Original, 1778 January 24 (Box 3, Folder 190)
  - ALS, Robert Morris to Richard Peters; introduces Dr. Shippen, relates that General Washington is being blackened unjustly; glad that Peters is staying clear of party politics. Photostatic Copy, 1778 January 25 (Box 3, Folder 191)
  - TLS, John Adams to Benjamin Rush, stating that Continental officers don't lack skill or bravery, but are wanting in diligence and patience. Typed Copy, 1778 February 8 (Box 3, Folder 192)
  - TLS, William Duer to Francis Lightfoot Lee, Duer had been accused by Lafayette of being a Tory, Duer feels dissolution of the Army is imminent. Copy, (1778) 1777 February 14 (Box 3, Folder 193)
  - TLS, Lund Washington to George Washington, tells of talking with Lee and that Congress has no plot planned against the Commander-in-Chief. States that flour should sell well. Typed photostatic copy, 1778 February 18 (Box 3, Folder 194)
  - ALS, T.P. to Colonel R.H. Harrison, need of supplies for the next campaign, an exchange of prisoners is about to take place. Why let healthy British troops go back to fight when all the Americans held prisoner are weak and sick. Photostatic Copy of Original, 1778 February 20 (Box 3, Folder 195)
  - ALS, Benjamin Rush to (George Washington?), talks of Dr. Shippen and his neglect of duty while Chief Physician and the action taken by Rush as new Chief Physician to correct them. Photostat of Original, 1778 February 25 (Box 3, Folder 196)
  - Receipt of money from William Paterson, total of twenty-two pounds. Signed Charles Pettit, 1778 March 4 (Box 3, Folder 197)
  - ALS, Thomas Conway to (Horatio Gates), wants to know why he should not be in the main action instead of a holding one. Photostat of Original, 1778 April 22 (Box 3, Folder 198)
  - ALS, George Lux to Major General Green, wishes Green luck in his new appointment, talks of the decline in Continental money, Arnold and Lincoln to serve with Washington, General Smallwood unpopular amongst the Maryland troops, General Sullivan transferred to Rhode Island. Photostat of Original, 1778 April 22 (Box 3, Folder 199)
  - ALS, Robert Christie (well known Tory merchant) to his father; tells of moving to New York and awaiting the arrival of a shipload of goods that he expects a good profit from. Tells his father to sell his tobacco for bills of exchange and not to try to export it, 1778 May 24 (Box 3, Folder 200)
  - ALS, Gen. Anthony Wayne to Polly Wayne; describes a battle with the British that eventually became an American victory. Photostat of Original, 1778 July 1 (Box 3, Folder 201)
  - ALS, Dr. H. Cooper to George Panton; tells of visit to Panton's parents in the Highlands; sends some money to Panton, asks to be remembered to the members of the Protestant Episcopal Church in America. With Photostat of Original, 1778 July 31 (Box 3, Folder 202)
  - Note of exchange for fifty-two pounds ten shillings to Major Laurence Parsons, Robert Jackson to James Jackson. Printed Form, 1778 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 203)
  - ALS, George Lux to Major General Greene; congratulations to Greene on safe retreat from Rhode Island; that will halt the cabal against Greene and Washington. Photostat of Original, 1778 October 24 (Box 3, Folder 204)
  - ALS, George Washington to [?]; indicates that recipient is in contact with a spy, also Washington tells how short and needed specie is. Photostatic copy, 1778 November 29 (Box 3, Folder 205)
  - ALS, James Darah to John Ladd Howell; tells of the shortage of salt and action to cope with the problem, 1778 November 29 (Box 3, Folder 206)
  - ALS, John Jameson to [?]; tells of transporting German prisoners, also of going to Philadelphia to settle his Will and accounts, complaints of British prisoners stealing food etc, 1778 December 5 (Box 3, Folder 207)
  - AL, [?] to [General Clinton]; British may try to divide and conquer, inaction in the Army and Government is dangerous. Tells of attempts to replace Washington. Photostat of Original, Undated [1778] (Box 3, Folder 208)